A portion of this video
was sponsored by Salesforce.
This is the biggest, most
in-depth video about bowling ever.
How bowling balls are made,
the best way to throw them,
maximize strikes, how the lanes are oiled,
what it takes to be a pro
and how this sport has
continually been reinvented
for literally thousands of
years, up to the present day.
(bowling strikes)
This is the science of bowling,
the most popular participatory
sport in the United States.
I'm super impressed with how that went.
- I'm even more impressed than you are.
- What is inside a bowling ball?
I sent this ball to Creative Electron
to get a 3D x-ray scan
and this is the result.
What is that?
I always expected bowling
balls to be, you know,
perfect solid spheres, but
there's something inside here
and it's not symmetric
and it's not even centered in the ball.
So I went to Storm Bowling,
one of only 11 bowling ball
manufacturers in the world
to find out how bowling balls are made.
- Yeah. Basically when
we make bowling balls,
we always start in the center
and the center part of the
bowling ball is the weight block.
And as you can see this is an example
of an asymmetrical shaped weight block,
so it's actually a different shape
about the X, the Y and the Z axis.
(serene music)
- The weight blocks are embedded
in a core of lightweight glass beads.
- That is so silky-soft.
I feel like I have not
felt anything this soft.
What's the difference in density between
this sort of filling
material and this core?
- It's quite a bit.
About two and a half to
three times more dense
in the inner weight block
than it is in the core material.
- If you were to look for
example at this actual core.
Number one, it says 9 6 0
which means that it weighs 9.60 pounds.
And then the description here underneath,
which is a 0 3,
this indicates what type of a
weight block is inside of it.
- What happens over here?
- So this area right here
is our urethane area.
So basically what we have
are a number of different
tanks that are set up.
So there's a chemical reaction that occurs
once it actually fills the mold
and we pour that cover stock
material around the pour.
It gets extremely hot in
just a matter of minutes.
You go right down here,
she's actually pouring the pin material
inside the tops of those cores.
So you can see for this
particular bowling ball,
it's a bright orange type of a material,
and she's actually filling that hole
with that plug material.
We've got the lane at the right here
which is where we take the
balls that come out of the mold.
And then they actually
spin almost 2000 RPM.
On top of there there's
the blades that come around
and it actually makes the
balls perfectly round.
So they'll actually trim those up.
- [Derek] Since the
balls are not symmetric,
they are heavier on one
side than the other.
- And you can see there the
last four or five pumps of air,
where it actually floats the
air then it stops and pauses,
that the ball has completely settled.
And then basically a needle will come out
from the bottom part
and all of a sudden it'll shoot it up.
And then it'll be where
the center of gravity is
on the surface of the ball.
- When it comes right
off the lane, right here,
it is extremely porous
and very, very dull,
and there is a ton of friction
between the ball and
the lane at this point.
So every ball from right
here will be smoothed up,
it's just a matter of how
much it's gonna be smoothed up
in order to get what
is the desired finish.
- [Derek] But before
they can use these balls,
they have to be drilled.
But that is specific to each bowler.
How many balls are you making a day?
- [Steve] We're making over
3000 balls in a day now.
they come out of this plant right here.
(smooth calm music)
- Wild.
I found the bowling ball
equivalent of clickbait.
"You won't believe your eyes",
"The mind bending hook".
- Right?
- Yeah.
It's how you have to sell your stuff.
I get it.
- Exactly. Yeah.
- [Derek] But how did
it come to be this way?
Well, bowling seems to be an ancient game.
Archeologists have found
wall drawings of a sport
that looks like bowling in
an ancient Egyptian tomb
dating back 7,000 years.
In Germany, bowling was
used as a religious ritual.
Pins represented your sins,
so you're a good Christian if
you could knock them all down.
Martin Luther himself was
apparently a bowling fanatic
and fixed the number of pins at nine.
When the game made its
way over to America,
nine-pin bowling was banned
because it promoted gambling.
The legend goes that people
cleverly came up with
10-pin bowling to get around the law.
Whoa, totally different game.
Today in the US, nine-pin
bowling is only played in Texas
because it was the one
state that didn't ban it,
instead, charging it tax.
Bowling lanes are about
three-and-a-half-feet wide
and 60 feet long down to the headpin.
I'm using Imperial units here
because that's actually
how they're defined.
The lane is made of 39 narrow boards
that bowlers number for reference.
They used to be made
of maple and pinewood,
but these days, most lanes are synthetic
and made of fine particles
coated with melamine resin.
One game of bowling gives you 10 frames
with two throws per frame
to try to knock down all 10 pins.
The highest score you can get
in a game without a strike
is only 190,
but strikes allow you to double
count your next two throws,
so a perfect game with all strikes
gives you a score of 300.
If you're anything like me,
如果你和我一样
the whole game is just
认为游戏的目的就是尽量让球走球道中央的直线
trying to throw the ball as straight as you can
down the middle of the lane, hit the headpin
并让球击中瓶堆中央的瓶
and try to take as many other pins down with it as possible.
并且让球尽可能多地击倒其他瓶
Do you wanna give me any tips or-
你能不能给我点提示……
- I've watched LeBron bowling,
you won't be worse than him.
我见过勒布朗打保龄球，你肯定比他好一些
- You say that now you.
这可是你说的
(Chris laughs)
- See, that's what I would normally do.
你看，这就是我平时的水平
And I would normally be like
打成这个样子我已经很开心了
reasonably happy with a shot like that.
But for pro-bowlers like
Pete Weber or Chris Barnes,
但是对于像皮特·韦伯和克里斯·巴恩斯这样的专业球员来说
- [Narrator] For a perfect game,
【解说】打得漂亮！
- Yes!
YES！
- [Derek] The game is different.
这完全不是相同的比赛
And not just because they are way better than me.
不止因为他们的水平比我高
- [Narrator] And he get it!
【解说】他做到了！
(crowd cheering)
- Who you think that you are? I am.
你以为你是谁？我才是那个谁！！
(crowd continues cheering)
Hitting the headpins square on
瞄准首瓶出球
is not the perfect strategy.
并不是最佳策略
If you hit the headpin square on going straight,
如果你瞄准了首瓶直线出球
you're unlikely to knock down all the pins.
就很难把瓶都击倒
You could end up with a split
剩下的球会分开留在两侧
where the ball goes through the middle,
球从中间穿过
or with the ball deflecting off to one side
或者球在击中首瓶之后
after hitting the headpin.
滚到一边
Chances for a strike are much higher
要想一击全中
if the center of the ball hits the pins
就要让球心击中首瓶的旁边的瓶
just to one side of the headpin.
Board 17 and a half.
在位于第17.5条木板的位置
In which case the ball takes
out the 1, 3, 5, and 9 pins,
此时球击中了第1、3、5和9号瓶
which take out the others.
这几个瓶再把其他的瓶击倒
- So we want the ball
to hit the 1 pin, the 3,
我想让球击中1号和3号瓶
the pin behind the 1, which is the 5 pin.
然后是1号瓶后面的5号
And then the 9 or the 8 and the 9.
然后是9号，或者8号9号一起
- [Derek] You want the ball to hit all of those pins?
球只要击倒这几个就行了？
- [Chris] Yeah.
对
- Now the pins don't always fall this way,
此时还没有击倒所有的瓶
but the pin shape helps.
但是保龄球瓶的特殊形状能帮忙
Pins roll in circles like eggs,
瓶倒下后会像鸡蛋一样转圈滚
which help knock down the others.
从而帮助击倒其他的瓶
- That's right baby!
好球！
Come on, don't miss.
来嘛，好戏不容错过
You wanted it, you got it.
只要我想，我就能得分！
- [Derek] But to have an over 90% chance
不过，为了得到九成以上的全中
of getting a strike,
the center of the ball has to hit
击中首瓶时的误差
with an error smaller than half a board.
不能超过半个木板的宽度
Needless to say, throwing a ball 60 feet
同时投球的距离有60英尺（18.288米）
straight at a target smaller than a dime is a tough task.
看上去目标也就一个硬币大
Especially to do it consistently.
而且要求发挥稳定
Luckily there is a better way.
还好有个捷径
- Now, if we look at the pins
如果你在这里看球瓶
and as you look at them
from here, from straight on,
站在这里朝前看
the spot between the headpin,
首瓶，也就是最中间的这个
the one that's in the center,
and the 3 pin which is just right at that,
和三号瓶，就是他旁边的这个
that gap's pretty narrow.
这两个瓶之间的空隙很小
But as the ball hooks more,
但是如果球路弯一点
now we basically shift over,
相当于从这个方向看过去
and now that space is considerably wider.
空隙就宽了不少
- [Derek] If you can hit the pins not head-on,
如果你不直直的朝着首瓶击球
but at an angle of six degrees,
而是偏转6度左右
you dramatically increase your chances
击球全中的概率就能明显提高不少
of knocking them all down.
Now the margin for error is greater.
此时投球误差可以稍微高一点了
The ball can be coming in
保龄球可以从第17到18.5条木板处击中球瓶
anywhere from board 17 to 18 and a half,
that is a board and a half of room.
总宽度达到了1.5条木板的宽度
And that still gives you
同时还能够保证你有九成以上的把握全中
greater than a 90% chance of a strike.
Now, six degrees may not sound like a lot,
不过6度听起来不多
but it's actually extremely difficult to hit.
可实际上还是很难达到的
The problem is, if you wanted to throw the ball
问题在于，如果你想以6度的角度
straight at the pins and
hit them at six degrees,
直线投球击中四号球道的球瓶的话
you would have to be bowling from 3/4 over on the next lane.
你得在五又四分之三号球道投球才行
And that is impossible.
一般人可做不到
Well, with the two gutters in between and all.
尤其是每条球道旁都有两条沟
So the solution is
解决的方法是
you've got to curve the ball on one lane.
在这条球道内，让球走弧线
I feel like I have never spun a ball.
好像我从来没有试过旋转发球
Is that, (Derek laughs)
这个
Is that hard?
这个难不难？
- So if you've got it under your hand
只要用手抓球
and the ball's underneath,
让球在手下面
and you're trying to spin it,
然后尝试旋转球
that's especially the motion that players use these days.
现在大多数球手都是这么发球的
- [Derek] This really became
这位保龄球运动带来了很大的不确定性
a big part of the sport by accident.
- The wood gets beat up
球是砸在木板上的
with the damage from all the balls going into it.
由于受到了球的撞击
And so they basically created slip agents,
而且木板上还有一层润滑剂
lubricants much like oil on a car
有点像给车打蜡
so that the lanes didn't get damaged so quickly.
让球道不会那么快受损
- [Derek] So the original idea was to protect the wood.
润滑剂最开始的目的是为了保护木板
- The original idea was
是的，最开始是为了保护球道的木板
just to protect the surface of the lane.
It was not to manufacture anything
并不是为了使比赛更有对抗性
for my competitive-scoring type environment.
- But applying oil to protect the wood
而是为了保护木板而涂油
meant that balls no longer grip the lane
导致了球不能很好的抓地
and roll without slipping down to the pins.
同时球也无法顺利旋转，击中球瓶
Instead they could skid,
而是会打滑
rotating not in their direction of travel.
使得无法沿着前进方向滚动
Now, I've been to a lot of bowling alleys
制作本期视频之前，我去了很多保龄球馆
before making this video
and I noticed it was a bit greasy,
我发现球道都有些油腻腻的
but I always thought that was just
我以为这些球道就是这样的
the nature of bowling alleys.
Like the stinky rental shoes.
就像那些臭烘烘的租赁球鞋一样
I didn't know they intentionally put oil on the lanes.
后来才发现这些由是专门涂上去的
Vox has a great video specifically about oil patterns.
Vox有一个专门介绍涂油的视频
These days, there are machines
现在有专门的机器用于在赛道上涂油
specifically for applying
oil to the lanes.
现在有专门的机器用于在赛道上涂油
- [Chris] And then as proprietors went,
后来场馆老板发现
"Huh, well yeah, it does make the ball skid.
“嗯，这样球会打滑”
Well, if I put more in the middle than the outside
“那我就在中间多涂点”
my baller's bowl a little bit better and they're happier."
“顾客发现球技提高了，也就更高兴了”
And then as technology advances like everything does
然后技术不断发展进步
now we have $30,000 lane machines
现在这台机器要三万刀
that can put a specific amount of oil on each board.
能够按照特定的方式涂油
- [Derek] They work kind of like dot matrix printers.
机器的工作方式有点类似针式打印机
They can lay the oil on
可以把油滴按照特定的角度和厚度喷在球道上
with varying degrees of thickness across the lane
and extend the oil pattern different distances.
这样在球道上就能形成不同图案
There are hundreds of different patterns that can be used.
涂油的图案有几百种，各不相同
Usually the oil extends about 2/3 the way down the lane,
一般来说只在球道前2/3涂油
so to around 40 or 45 feet.
大约40到45英尺（12.19米到13.72米）
But there's always a dry patch of wood before the pins
不过在球道末端总有一段是干的
that increases the friction with the ball,
用于增加和球的摩擦
getting it to start rolling without slipping.
让球可以开始滚动，不再打滑
And this leads to the three  parts of any pro bowler's throw.
这就是专业球手的三大致胜诀窍
The skid,
the hook
and the roll.
When a bowler releases the ball,
it can be going 20 miles an hour
and spinning at 500 RPM.
That's nearly 10 full
revolutions per second.
Right-handers typically
throw the ball to the right
on the lane while spinning it to the left.
During the skid phase, the
ball slides down the lane
spinning but not rolling.
As it comes to the end of the oil,
the friction increases and the
ball accelerates to the left.
It hooks because of its spin,
and the spin starts lining up
with the direction of travel,
leading to stage three, roll.
The ball is rolling without slipping
as it barrels into the pins.
Ideally, as close to that
six degree angle as possible.
Like the ball starts on
the left side of the lane,
goes straight across almost rightmost.
Then hooks like at the last
minute, rolls in there.
So that's almost like
a perfect shot, right?
straight in the pocket there.
- Close.
- Yeah. That's where you
want to hit the pins.
Yeah.
(ball hits the floor)
- My very first game,
it was ABC back then,
American Bowling Congress.
I filled out the application
to bowl in men's league.
Dad gave them the letter
saying that I could,
and the first game of bowl was 300
and they handed me a hundred dollars too,
and it was like, yeah, making money now.
And actually, my first,
my sixth, my ninth,
my 13th, 17th, 20th
were all 300 games.
I like, seven or eight 300
in my first year of men's league.
- [Derek] How do you explain that?
- To shoot 300
you have to get lucky
somewhere along the line.
Like that.
(Derek laughs)
It came in to hit the 1 3, 5, 9.
And that that's what we
call the perfect shot.
- I mean, you just keep hitting them.
That's almost the identical shot.
Look at that, that yellow and the purple,
they're almost exactly
on top of each other.
- Oh, it just goes a little bit straight.
- That one, the purple one
was just a little bit
higher on the head pin,
but it still hit the 1,
3 and the 5 and the 9.
Can't get much better.
- [Derek] This type of
throw is only possible
because of the oil.
If you try to throw a ball the
same way on an unoiled lane.
Oh no.
It just doesn't work.
Can I actually ask you to
bowl like you normally would,
but on the dry lane?
I know it's crazy.
I just want to see what like
a normal shot would look like
If there was no oil.
- No oil.
It's gonna hit the lane
and go in the left gutter.
- That's what I want to see.
- All right.
You're gonna throw it just
like it's a regular lane.
- Yeah.
- All right.
- Oh yeah, there's no oil on the lane
so the ball can't get down.
As soon as it hits the lane,
it's going to start hooking, you know?
'Cause if you do this, who's
skidding a ball on this.
- So they want the oil.
- Yeah. We need the oil.
If we didn't have oil,
this is what it would be.
And nobody would have fun.
This is not fun.
- The bowling sucks,
We don't want to do this.
(Derek laughs)
- For pro bowlers, the oil on the lane
is a key part of the game.
- Oh whoa.
- Wow. Hey.
- Do you look at the oil?
Are you trying to scope it out
or are you just kind of guessing?
- I usually don't look at the oil.
I let my ball be the guide.
You know, I know some guys that are,
you know, they get down
like this and they look in
and it's like, oh, you know,
they're seeing the same thing I do
when I sit down, I go like that.
Nothing.
I see absolutely nothing.
- Whether you can see it or not,
figuring out the condition
of oil on the lane
can make the difference
between a strike and a miss.
As the game wears on the bowling
balls move the oil around,
pushing it further down the lane
and stripping it off
the most common paths.
So players have to adjust
to the changing conditions.
Some people say left-handers
have an advantage
because right-handers aren't playing
on their side of the lane.
At most bowling alleys,
they use a pattern of oil
that is thicker in the middle
and thinner out toward the edges.
This is a forgiving layout
because balls that drift too
far out start to hook earlier,
while balls going straighter
can continue down the lane for longer
before making their turn into the pins.
But for pro bowlers,
the oil conditions vary
and players have to adjust
their games to the conditions.
Some people seem to think
that like league bowlers
are better than they are, maybe,
'cause they say like,
"Oh, this league bowler
can shoot two 10, and I
just saw pro shoot two 10."
- That's why they call it league
because you bowl on the
same shot every week.
Because each week on tour,
I'm bowling on a different condition.
Not the same condition every week.
We have Cheetah,
Chameleon, Scorpion, shark,
one more.
- Bear?
- Bear. Yeah.
- [Derek] But it's not
just the oil on the lanes
that is transformed bowling.
It's also the balls themselves.
- Hard rubber bowling balls
was what I started with.
Maybe mid 70's and then the Yellow Dot,
the Columbia Yellow Dot,
which is a plastic ball.
And then they came out with
urethane bowling balls.
I won a lot of titles
with the urethane stuff.
And then they come out with the
reactive resin bowling balls.
- [Derek] Reactive resin is
just a modified polyurethane
with a more porous surface,
which gives it more grip in the oil.
It's the most popular
surface or cover stock
for bowling balls today.
Balls started out as perfect
symmetrically-weighted spheres.
And when you go to a bowling alley,
the house balls there are still just that.
But when you drill holes in the ball,
you take some weight out of one side.
So to rebalance it, ball manufacturers
added a small pancake weight
on the same side as the holes.
But then ball manufacturers got the idea,
they could add different
weights inside the ball
to improve their performance.
You can have two balls that
look identical from the outside,
weigh exactly the same amount,
and yet roll differently.
If the mass is more concentrated
around the axis of rotation,
say you have a dense
cylinder inside the ball.
Well then it has a
lower moment of inertia.
And this means for the same
amount of energy input,
it will spin faster.
In bowling, they prefer to talk
about an analogous concept.
Radius of gyration or RG.
If you were to concentrate
the entire mass of the ball
onto a hoop with the
same moment of inertia,
it's radius would be
the radius of gyration.
So smaller radius of gyration
just means lower moment of inertia,
which translates into more rotation
that a bowler can get on the ball.
- Some people are lower leverage
it just spins faster, like,
eh, it's of crazy, and then
somebody finally did a study on that.
Yeah, it turns out,
yeah, it's like 8%, you
know, for every 0.05.
And so it depends on
what your leverage is.
Can be fairly significant.
- [Derek] An ability to
spin the balls faster,
gives a bowler the
ability to hook the ball
more sharply further down the lane,
giving them a better chance of achieving
that six degree entry angle.
What was amazing for me to learn
is that the weight blocks in these balls
aren't even centered.
There's a heavy side and
a lighter side on purpose,
and you can find and mark this side
by letting the ball spin
freely on a cushion of air,
until it comes to rest, heavy side down.
They showed me a great demonstration
of how the position of
the center of gravity
can affect the movement of the ball.
When the center of mass is
on the left side of the ball,
it pulls in the same
direction as the spin,
helping the ball hook to
the left, into the pins,
- Same exact ball, same numbers,
just different static
and balance basically.
- [Derek] But here is
a flipped bowling ball
where the center of mass is on the right.
Now the ball starts to hook into the left,
but at the end, something weird happens.
The center of mass pulls
it over to the right.
This effect is only really noticeable
when the ball is thrown slowly.
These days, there are tons
of different weight blocks
that go inside bowling balls
and they can be grouped
into two categories,
symmetric and asymmetric.
For all these weight blocks,
the minimum moment of inertia
or in bowling terms, the smallest RG axis
is identified by a pin,
which is visible on the
outside of the ball.
It will spin most easily about this axis.
For the symmetric weight blocks.
The ball doesn't change as
you rotate it about this axis.
So the maximum moment of inertia
is rotating about any axis that passes
through the equator of the ball.
I certainly didn't expect bowling balls
to have asymmetric cores,
but it turns out what
looked like perfect spheres,
actually have three different
principal axes of rotation.
Minimum moment of inertia,
maximum moment of inertia
and intermediate moment of inertia.
- So this right here is our Dark Code.
This is one of our asymmetric ball
that has the Rad 4 core in it.
So this has a preferred spin axis.
And what we're going to do now
is we're going to put
it onto the determinator
and show how it actually
will spin it and find it
no matter how we position it on there.
- [Derek] So you spin
them up on this machine
until they settle into
the way they like to spin
where the bowlers call their
preferred spin axis or PSA.
But why would you want a
ball to be an asymmetric top?
Well, professional
bowlers drill their balls
so that at lunch the axis of
rotation is somewhere between
the minimum and maximum moment of inertia.
And as a result, as the ball
goes down the lane spinning,
it precesses like a gyroscope.
The axis of rotation rotates around
causing the point of contact
between the ball and the lane to change.
This precession means that
different parts of the
ball contact the lane.
And you can see this when the ball back
by the spread-out lines of
oil on the ball surface.
Bowlers call this track flare,
and it's desirable because it means
once the ball hits the
unoiled part of the lane,
it gets traction faster
and hooks more dramatically
back to the pins.
This is what asymmetric
cores are used for.
They have larger differences
between their moments of
inertia in different axes
or what bowlers call RG differential,
which makes the ball precess.
If you spin a ball around it's minimum
or maximum moment of
inertia, it processes less
and there's much less flair,
meaning oil builds up
on one part of the ball.
This reduces the friction
over the dry part of the lane
so the ball hooks less.
- See the oil there, very faintly,
but it's pretty much next to the finger,
right next to the thumb,
and it just continues to be right that way
all the way around the ball.
- [Derek] But how important are
each of these factors in
actually getting the best shot?
Well, the US Bowling Congress,
or USBC, the governing
body that sets all rules
and regulations for US bowling.
They did a landmark study in 2008,
trying to tease out the
most significant factors
that affect ball motion.
In order to determine the
impact of each factor,
they had to make sure that
throws were identical.
So they turned to Harry,
at the time, the most
consistent bowler in the world.
He is a robot.
Bowling robots are designed
to be able to throw
hundreds of identical shots.
In fact, the robot Earl,
Harry's successor in 2011,
actually lost to Chris
Barnes when he debuted
in part because his
throws were so consistent.
He wore away the oil in a
single part of the lane.
So his shots hooked too much.
The people managing him
did their best to adjust
to the oil conditions,
but few people are Chris Barnes.
The USBC ball motion study
used Harry to throw thousands of shots
with different bowling balls.
And they found that the center of gravity
affected the ball motion
relatively little.
Around the same level
as environmental factors
like room temperature or humidity.
RG, and RG differential,
essentially the moment of inertia
and difference between maximum
and minimum moments of inertia.
That affected the ball
motion significantly more.
But the factor that affected
ball motion the most
was the surface of the ball.
The top five individual factors were
the amplitude of surface roughness,
meaning the height of
microscopic spikes on the ball,
the coefficient of friction
with an oiled lane,
the surface roughness by spacing.
That is the distance
between microscopic spikes,
the coefficient of
friction with the dry lane,
and how quickly the ball
surface absorbs oil.
Now, bowlers recognize just how important
the surface of their ball is.
They pay close attention
to what it's made of
and how it's finished.
Rougher finishes,
give the ball more traction in the oil
and get it to start hooking earlier.
This is useful for long oil patterns
and slower axis rotation.
- Sometimes maybe I'll go
to a little more sanded ball
or a little more ball surface
to get it into a roll quicker for me,
because they use a lot of oil.
- These two shots are thrown identically.
The only difference is
the ball on the left
has a rougher surface.
Rough surfaces act like winter tires,
helping to dig into the oil
and give the ball traction.
They also act as badly as
winter tires on a clean road
on a totally dry lane.
They actually have less friction
because their rougher exteriors
mean that less surface
area is touching the lane.
You can get many different
levels of smoothness
up to a near mirror shine.
This is better for short oil patterns
to prevent the ball hooking
too much, too early.
Ultimately, pro bowlers
carry many different balls
to each competition.
- I'm not afraid to change
balls in the middle of the game.
I go to the game and I've got like
a spare, a spare, a spare.
All right. It's time to change balls.
- [Derek] Yeah.
- So now I gotta find the right ball to
get down the lane again
and find the proper,
which usually I have a pretty good idea.
- [Derek] So they select their ball
a little like a golfer selects their club,
to suit the conditions.
But does all this tech actually
make people better bowlers?
Well, over the last 20 years,
average scores have increased
by more than five points.
Plus the number of perfect 300 games
bowled per year per thousand bowlers
has increased dramatically
since the 1980s.
This graph shows the percent
change year over year.
In 1976, soaker balls,
balls chemically softened
to absorb oil and hook more,
were banned, and there was
a dip in perfect games.
But the same year a new
rubber ball was introduced,
the Brunswick LT-48
and more 300 were hit in
the years that followed.
In 1991, reactive resin
balls were introduced
and there was another significant jump.
Now, obviously there were
other improvements in equipment
and natural variability,
but some of the big changes do correlate
with the introduction
of new ball technology.
So yes, the wild bowling
ball technologies out there,
especially anything to do with surface,
significantly affect ball
motion and your bowling game.
But ball motion is
likely minutely affected
by hundreds of other factors.
Even the color of the ball
can have a small impact.
A USBC study in 2016
found that different pigments
absorb oil at different rates.
Bowling is the sport of re-invention.
That goes back to ancient Egypt,
but has transformed many times.
Now, when you get up
to throw a single shot,
you have to think about the
oil pattern on the lane,
the stage of the game and
how the pattern has shifted,
the weight block in your ball,
whether you want symmetric or asymmetric,
which axis you'll spin it
about to affect precession,
where the center of mass is
to pull the ball to
the left, to the right,
what the cover stock is made of
and whether it's rough or smooth,
all to make a shot that
skids, hooks, and rolls
to the pins between boards
17 and 18 and a half
at as close to a six degree
angle as you can master.
Now do that again 12 times in a row
and you have a perfect game.
(techno sound effect)
Hey, this portion of the video
was sponsored by Salesforce.
Bowling may be complicated,
but managing relationships
with your customers
doesn't have to be.
In our modern work-from-anywhere world,
Salesforce makes it
easier for your business
to meet the needs of your customers.
You can help them find
answers about your business
by creating a help center page.
You can also meet your
customers where they're at
by connecting your email,
phone and social channels.
You probably spend a lot
of time on your website,
So make it work harder for you
by leveraging lead capture
forms from Salesforce
right on your site.
And you'll be able to
generate new business
and develop relationships
with your customers
straight from your CRM.
Sending out messages or
special promos is easy.
Salesforce has a whole
array of personalization
and message targeting options.
So you can request a demo
or get started for just
$25 per user per month
at salesforce.com/veritasium.
I want to thank Salesforce
for sponsoring this portion of the video,
and I want to thank you for watching.